<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: flatiron | Blogj!]]></title>
  <link href="http://jayzee.github.io/blog/categories/flatiron/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jayzee.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-23T14:03:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jayzee.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Zizmor]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Group By &amp;&amp; Having == ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jayzee.github.io/blog/2016/02/20/group-by-and-and-having-equals-equals/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-20T21:41:16-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jayzee.github.io/blog/2016/02/20/group-by-and-and-having-equals-equals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to take a few minutes to discuss the GROUP BY function and the HAVING function. I&rsquo;ll try to answer the questions around when should they be used? What do they &lsquo;really&rsquo; do and why should we use them.</p>

<p>But first &hellip; ROTHKO!</p>

<p><img src="https://www.etc.cmu.edu/projects/atl/images/rothko/rothko3.jpg"></p>

<p>Why Rothko? His work highlights the importance of carefully choosing the items that group together. By &ldquo;grouping&rdquo; specific colors  the piece as a whole is stronger than the individual color. Grouping or picking the right items that go together can heighten or take away from a group. 1 + 1 = 3 or 1 + 1 = -2.</p>

<p><img src="https://sprungonfood.files.wordpress.com/2014/08/image_36.jpeg"></p>

<p>Same with food, eating a meal that has flavors that complement each other can bring the plate to the next level (salty and sweet is a killer&hellip; shout out to salted crack caramel ice cream).</p>

<p><strong>1. Group By</strong></p>

<p>What’s up with GROUP BY? Is it as straightforward as it sounds or is there some dark layer hiding underneath that will haunt your SQL statement and return you &lsquo;brie&rsquo; when you were expecting &lsquo;Gouda&rsquo;. SQL acts like its as straight forward as vanilla but we all know there&rsquo;s some chunky monkey hiding beneath the surface.</p>

<p>Basics:</p>

<p>Lots of times we have more than one record for a certain attribute. For example, there could be 25 players on the Yankees  in a league with hundreds of players and I just want to know the best on base percentage for the yankees.</p>

<p>OR what if need to know the total sick days for 5 members of the custodial staff in a company of 150 employees.</p>

<p>OR what if I&rsquo;m trying to see how many current members are in Earth Wind &amp; Fire from a database that has that everyone who has ever played in the group.</p>

<p>GROUP BY is the key to finding out this kind of information</p>

<p>GROUP BY gathers all of the rows together that contain data in the specified column and will allow aggregate functions to happen to one more columns.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say you are in charge of a zoo. Let&rsquo;s call it the Flatiron Zoo for discarded animals. You put together a nice database that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="sql.png"></p>

<pre><code>Animal      Qty     Favorite Food      Bites?     Type
Duck          5         PopTarts        No       Mammal
Kangaroo    10        Granola         Yes        Mammal
Iguanas    4          Salad           No         Reptile
Frog      30        licorice      No       Amphibian
</code></pre>

<p>Let’s say I’d like to see how many Mammals I have at my small zoo. I’d want to have a row just for animal types. That’s where GROUP BY can come in handy. I can SUM the items in my select and only show one row of Animal Type.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say I ran this SQL code:
<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>SELECT Animal_Type, SUM(QTY) FROM Animals_in_Zoo
</span><span class='line'>GROUP BY Animal_Type&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
</span><span class='line'>There must be some common missteps that people make, right?
</span><span class='line'>Let's say you run this SQL statement:
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;SELECT * FROM Animals_in_zoo
</span><span class='line'>GROUP BY type</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>You would get a highly dubious table that looks something like this:
<code>
Animal      Qty     Favorite Food      Bites?     Animal_Type
Duck          5         PopTarts        No       Mammal
Iguanas    4          Salad           No         Reptile
Frog      30        licorice      No       Amphibian
</code></p>

<p>It probably wouldn&rsquo;t be much help since it&rsquo;s basically just given us one row for each animal type.</p>

<p>Now More ROTHKO</p>

<p><img src="http://i.huffpost.com/gen/1849091/thumbs/o-MARK-ROTHKO-facebook.jpg"></p>

<p><strong>2. HAVING</strong>
So what&rsquo;s the deal with using HAVING. I know it replaces WHERE sometimes but what&rsquo;s the rule&hellip; when should I be using it?</p>

<ol>
<li>Where does not work with aggregates&hellip; For example:
SELECT animal_type, sum(Qty) from Animals_in_zoo
GROUP BY animal_type WHERE sum(qty) > 10</li>
</ol>


<p>This does not work. You need a HAVING instead of WHERE
SELECT animal_type, sum(Qty) from Animals_in_zoo
GROUP BY animal_type HAVING sum(qty) > 10</p>

<ol>
<li>One of the SELECT items has an AS after it.</li>
</ol>


<p>SELECT animal_type, animal AS animalize from Animals_in_zoo
GROUP BY animal_type HAVING animalize = &lsquo;Duck&rsquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Injection of Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://jayzee.github.io/blog/2016/02/08/my-first-post-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-08T18:11:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jayzee.github.io/blog/2016/02/08/my-first-post-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before last week I was convinced that at a fundamental level everything could be built of some combination of an if, else and while loop. I ignored higher level enumerators at all cost. As soon as I saw Ruby&rsquo;s inject method I instinctively tried to avoid it. It seemed confusing and unnecessary. Maybe there were some “advanced” coders who used it but I’m sure I could get around ever needing it.</p>

<p>At some point during last week&rsquo;s lab I was prodded into using it and very quickly the learning curve disappeared and it became a go-to tool.<br></p>

<p>Enumerable#inject is a powerful shortcut, it’s makes summing up items simple and compact.<br></p>

<p>The basics of inject can be done without .inject but it&rsquo;s really clunky. For example:<br></p>

<pre><code>counter = 5
sum = 0
while counter &lt;= 10
  sum += 5
  counter += 1
end
return sum
</code></pre>

<p>Inject is an iterating device lets you pass in a variable that can then be acted upon by all the items that are iterated through. Think of it like a class variable that stays throughout the laps of iteration. Inject then returns the variable which can be the sum of all the laps of iteration.<br></p>

<p>A basic example would work like this:
```
[2,3,4].inject() do | accumulator, item|
  accumulator += item
end</p>

<h1>=> 9</h1>

<pre><code>
Every item in the range is passed into the inject method. The block is executed one for each element that the inject is called up. In this case the range array has the numbers 2,3 and 4. The block will be executed upon 3 times. The first time the variable ‘item’ will be ‘2’, the second time ‘3’ and the third ‘4’. In each execution the ‘item’ will be added to the ‘accumulator’ variable. Inject is an easy way to sum up all the items in the array! &lt;br&gt;

Inject can also be passed a variable so that your ‘accumulator’ doesn’t need to to start at 0. Take a look at this example. &lt;br&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>[2,3,4].inject(20) do | accumulator, item|
  accumulator += item
end</p>

<h1>=> 29</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>The ‘accumulator’ variable is going to start at 20. This information is set directly to the right of the inject method.<br></p>

<p>Inject is now my go to code of choice when summing up items is needed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
